Guide to the UH Women's Organizations
University of Houston Libraries
UH Women's Organizations
1962-1994
09/1969-038
University of Houston Women’s Association, 1962-1994
3.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The University of Houston Women's Association Collection contain records of the organization from its founding in 1962 through 1994. The bulk of the materials date from the 1980s. Most of the UHWA papers consist of paper documents, with a few photographs.
Biographical Information:
The Faculty Wives Club and the Woman's Club of the University of Houston combined in 1962 to form the University of Houston Women's Association (UHWA). The UHWA provided a social and service organization for the wives of faculty and staff, and an ever-increasing number of female university faculty. Throughout each academic year the UHWA arranged various large-scale activities such as swimming parties, dinner theaters, and dances for its members, of which numbers usually ranged from two to three hundred dues-paying members. Smaller interest-based group functions included bridge games, book clubs, sewing parties, and gourmet cooking lessons. The organization also supported the student population through service events. The most notable of these is the Mary Harding Hoffman scholarship established in 1978. The scholarship provided children of University of Houston faculty or staff with tuition for their freshman year at the University of Houston on a merit basis.
An annually-elected executive board of officers led the University of Houston Women’s Association. The primary officers, consisting of a President, Vice President, Secretary, and Treasurer directed the affairs of the UHWA through smaller committees. The most consistently active committees during the organization's history included the newcomers, scholarship, and activities committees. The activities group also subdivided into smaller units gathering members with similar interests such as bridge, sewing, reading, and bowling.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston
Genre/Form of Material:
Business records
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Scope and Contents
The University of Houston Women's Association Collection contain records of the organization from its founding in 1962 through 1994. The bulk of the materials date from the 1980s. Most of the UHWA papers consist of paper documents, with a few photographs. The collection is arranged chronologically within each series, adhering as much as possible to the original order. However, the organizations of some items varied with the majority of the material, resulting in slight reordering. Materials regarding the Faculty Wives' Club, the Women's Club of the University of Houston, and the American Association of University Women, initially found among the UHWA documents, were removed and arranged in separate collections. The researcher may find it helpful to examine these smaller collections as well as the University of Houston Women's Association Papers.
The twelve series of the UHWA papers each follow the chronological order of the overall collection. The series are: the Executive Board, Business Meeting Minutes, Financial Records, Mary H. Hoffman Scholarship, Membership, Publicity, Activities, Newsletters, Correspondence, Photographs, Yearbooks, and Miscellaneous.
Detailed List of Contents
- Executive Board, 1962-1994
  Scope and Contents
  There are twenty-three folders in this series which contain the UHWA’s administrative guidelines and by-laws. Also included are lists of executive board members, executive board meeting agendas and minutes.
  - Administrative Guidelines, Constitution, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Guidelines, Position Descriptions, 1968-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Guidelines, History Outline, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Members (Membership Lists), 1969-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Members (Miscellaneous), 1973-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agenda, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agenda, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agenda, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Business Meeting Minutes, 1962-1992
  There are six folders in this series. The majority of minutes record events of the UHWA's Fall and Spring business meetings.
  - 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Financial Records, 1962-1994
  There are thirty-five folders in this series. The financial records series contains budgets, bank statements, treasurer's reports, books of check stubs, and receipts.
  - Budgets, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bank Statements, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bank Statements, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bank Statements, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bank Statements, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Receipts, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Receipts, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Receipts, January 1982-June 1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Receipts, July 1982-December 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Receipts, January 1983-April 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Receipts, July 1983-December 1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Receipts, January 1984-April 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Receipts, August 1984-December 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Receipts, January 1985-April 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, August 1985-December 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, January 1986-June 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Receipts, July 1986-December 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, January 1987-May 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Receipts, August 1987-April 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Check Registers, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Check Stubs, June 1982-April 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Check Stubs, August 1984-January 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Check Stubs, March 1986-November 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Mary H. Hoffman Scholarship, 1978-1994
  There are thirteen folders in this series which contains information about the Mary Hoffman Scholarship from its founding in 1978 through 1994. The series is particularly strong in documenting the establishment of the scholarship, including initial fund-raising efforts. Financial records for the scholarship are separate from those dealing with the general financial affairs of the University of Houston Women's Association.
  - April 1978-March 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - April 1979-October 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - January 1980-October 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - January 1981-September 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - March 1982-December 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - January 1983-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - January 1985-September 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - January 1987-August 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Membership, 1962-1990
  There are eleven folders in this series. The series includes lists of members as well as new faculty and staff lists which the newcomer committee used to recruit members. Box 4, Folder 7 contains a black, leather-bound ledger dating from 1950-1973, containing lists of dues-paying members as well as the amount paid. This item predates the UHWA but is labeled “UH Women's Association Membership 1950-1973,” and therefore is filed with this organization’s membership files. There is also a miscellaneous sub-division in this series. The miscellaneous folder contains registration forms, advertising flyers, and listings of important Houston-area organizations, emergency services, and events.
  - Lists, 1962-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lists, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lists, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lists, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lists, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lists, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lists (Black Ledger), 1950-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newcomer Letters, 1964-1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newcomer Letters, 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newcomer Letters, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975-1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Publicity, 1967-1989
  There are seven folders in this series which include press releases from the 1960s, 1970s, and early 1980s. The series also contains newspaper clippings from various Houston-area newspapers as well as University of Houston system and campus publications.
  - Press Releases, 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Press Releases, 1972-1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Houston area), 1967-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Houston area), undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Daily Cougar), 1977-1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clippings (Miscellaneous UH Publications), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Published Messages from Other Sources, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Activities, 1966-1994
  There are fourteen folders in this series which consists of programs and information regarding the various activities, calendars of events, and reports written by members evaluating the different activities.
  - Programs and Information, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Programs and Information, 1971-1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Programs and Information, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Programs and Information, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Programs and Information, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Programs and Information, January 1989 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Programs and Information, February 1989-November 1989 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Programs and Information, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Programs and Information, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Programs and Information, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Calendars, 1963-1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Calendars, 1988-1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Calendars, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reports, 1981-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, 1962-1994
  There are thirty-one folders in this series containing a fairly complete set of monthly or bi-monthly UHWA newsletters from the first edition in late 1962 through March 1994. The newsletters are arranged by academic year. Most of the issues are present with the exception of a few missing monthly editions and the partial academic years of 1974/75, 1975/76, 1976/77, and 1977/78.
  - September 1962-May 1964 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - September 1964-June 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - September 1965-June 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - September 1966-June 1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - September 1967-May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - September 1968-May 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - September 1969-May 1970 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - September 1970-April 1971 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - October 1971-March 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - September 1972-April 1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - September 1973-April 1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - May 1975-May 1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - September 1976-May 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - September 1977-July 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - September 1978-May 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - August 1979-May 1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - September 1980-March 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - September 1981-April 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - August 1982-April 1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - September 1983-April 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - September 1984-April 1985 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - September 1985-April 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Academic Year 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - September 1987-April 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Academic Year 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - October 1989-February 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - October 1990-March 1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - September 1991-May 1992 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - September 1992-April 1993 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - September 1993-March 1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1961-1994
  There are thirteen folders in this series. Formal correspondence, comprised mostly of letters received by the organization, date from 1961 through 1992. Informal correspondence includes a large number of thank you and sympathy cards of various dates, with the majority dated during the 1970s.
  - Formal, 1961-1967 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Formal, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Formal, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Formal, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Formal, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Formal, 1981-1985 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Formal, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Formal, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Formal, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Informal, 1966-1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Informal, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Informal, 1980-1994 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Informal, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1954, 1982, 1983, undated
  There are six folders in this series. The photographs contain both color snapshots and some black and white pictures.
  - 1954 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Yearbooks, 1962-1993
  There are eleven folders in this series. Yearbooks include a listing of the UHWA's constitution, a complete roster of members (including telephone numbers, department or spouse’s department, and address), and a variety of other information, depending on the year. Each yearbook encompasses an academic year and ranges from 1962-1963 through 1993-1994, excluding the school years of: 1971/72, 1972/73, 1974/75, 1980/81, 1984/85 through 1987/88, and 1992/93.
  - 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - 1974, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - 1984, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - 1992, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, 1968-1993
  This series contains four folders of material. Contents of the folders include items such as: Internal Revenue Service tax identification number forms, bulk mail rate applications, an announcement from a basketball game about the UHWA and the Mary H. Hoffman Scholarship, various surveys and invitations, and undated, handwritten notes. Also included in the grouping is a spiral notebook labeled “President's Report”. The notebook contains UHWA Presidents’ comments on the organization’s activities from 1968-1972, as well as some newspaper clippings.
  - 1968-1992 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - 1983-1993 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - President's Spiral-Bound Report, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
- UHWA Board binders, 1993-2007
  Materials in the binders consist of the same types of materials found in other series, but are being kept in original order in Series 13.
  - Board binders and organizational information (Box 8, Item 1)
- Unprocessed materials